Today's דף daf is דף צח, Daf Tzadik Chet, צח. Tzach. צח
וישר. Tzach veYashar. Okay, צח וישר. Tzach veYashar. Anyway,
we pick up about, whoa, we're about a little bit into it.
We pick up with במתניתא תנא. B'masnisa Tana. The line starts, it's
like after the line that begins with the asterisk about ten lines
down. משלימים, Mashlimim, one line lower, במתניתא תנא. B'masnisa Tana. So basically
the question was, how do we know this הלכה halacha that
when a חטאת chatas touches something and it gets, some of the
taste gets absorbed, that the new thing takes on the status of
the חטאת? chatas? As we said, it's sort of a principle that
is going to have broad applications for כשרות kashrus issues. It's only
in the תורה Torah said by a חטאת chatas and a מנחה.
mincha. So how do we know to apply it more broadly to
other קרבנות? korbanos? And the גמרא Gemara quoted this from שמואל, Shmuel,
what seems to be a
ברייתא, braisa, that the, you know, based on the פסוק pasuk of
זאת התורה לעלה
למנחה ולחטאת ולאשם ולמלואים ולזבח השלמים, Zos HaTorah La'Olah ulaMincha v'laChatas v'laAsham
v'laMiluim uleZevach HaShelamim, that we learn things from each one of those
קרבנות korbanos and the זאת התורה Zos HaTorah allows us to apply
it to all the קרבנות. korbanos. And what we learn from חטאת
chatas is this הלכה halacha about if things get absorbed. We learned
fascinating things about other things, particularly we pointed out yesterday about the
whole עולה olah that we learn that you use a כלי, kli,
a שחיטה shechitah knife, maybe even a כלי שרת, kli shares, and
bringing in the whole עקידת יצחק Akeidas Yitzchak is part of the
story of the עולה. olah. Was it from יצחק, Yitzchak, was it
from the ram, and so on. Anyway, but that we learn out
important הלכות halachos from each one of those קרבנות korbanos to apply
across the board. And from חטאת chatas we learn our הלכה. halacha.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues with the following. במתניתא
תנא, B'masnisa Tana, a ברייתא braisa we taught, משמיה דרבי עקיבא, mishmei
d'Rabbi Akiva, in the name of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, that actually
we learn out the idea of absorption and taking on the status
to other קרבנות korbanos not from חטאת, chatas, but from מנחה mincha
because the תורה Torah says it by both. So מנחה, mincha, מה
מנחה ma mincha again going to the פסוק pasuk of זאת התורה
לעלה למנחה, Zos HaTorah La'Olah ulaMincha, מה
מנחה מתקדשת בבלוע, ma mincha miskadeshes b'valu'a, the same way מנחה mincha
when something absorbs the מנחה mincha takes on its status, אף כל
מתקדשת בבלוע. af kol miskadeshes b'valu'a. So now you apply it to
other קרבנות korbanos as well as opposed to learning from מנחה mincha
that it's eaten by male כהנים, Kohanim, which really there was only
one thing to apply it to, which because everything it says that
eaten by male כהנים, Kohanim, you know, it says it explicitly. So
there yesterday we learned out from מנחה mincha that that applies to
the שלמי צבור, Shlamei Tzibbur, so and there was another source of
that idea that it applies to שלמי צבור Shlamei Tzibbur from קרח.
Korach. So here it says, you know what, let's learn that out
from קרח, Korach, the idea of male כהנים Kohanim for שלמי צבור.
Shlamei Tzibbur. For מנחה mincha we're going to learn out our הלכה.
halacha. For מנחה mincha we're going to learn out this הלכה halacha
that something that absorbs it, the, you know, it, it takes on
that status. Okay? So now we could learn it either from מנחה
mincha or from חטאת. chatas. And now the גמרא Gemara is going
to say the
following. ואיצטריך למכתב מנחה ואיצטריך למכתב חטאת. V'itztarech l'michtav mincha v'itztarech l'michtav
chatas.
מנחה Mincha also tells you that it's מתקדשת בבלוע miskadeshes b'valu'a in
מנחה.
mincha. I'd have to look it up, but it's right there in
צו. Tzav. Go, you know, go ahead and check, okay? So,
so the גמרא Gemara says ואיצטריך למכתב מנחה ואיצטריך למכתב חטאת. v'itztarech
l'michtav mincha v'itztarech l'michtav chatas. And it had to say both. Okay,
you could have said maybe now חטאת chatas is free to teach
you something else. But the גמרא Gemara is actually saying, let's, let's
embrace both of these ברייתות. braisas. Let's embrace the idea that you
learn it out from חטאת chatas from זאת התורה Zos HaTorah and
you learn it out from מנחה, mincha, זאת התורה. Zos HaTorah. And
now why, and you need both. Why do you need both? דאי
אשמעינן מנחה, D'ee ashmi'inan mincha, had it just said מנחה, mincha, איידי
דרכיכא מבלע, aydi d'rechicha mivla, okay, maybe it applies to a מנחה
mincha because it's, it's you know, it's like soft. So it gets
absorbed, you know,
so maybe maybe it's at an earlier stage?
Not at a later stage?
Right, not after it's baked, that's true. But when it's, when it's
just the flour and the oil. אבל חטאת אימא לא, Aval chatas
ayma lo, but a חטאת chatas maybe not.
Okay, so you know maybe the thing I'm just realizing, I assumed
what it meant was that the thing that is, the A that's
transferring into B, A is soft. But it might actually be referring
to the fact that B, B is softer and it's easier to
absorb.
How do they translate it there, David? I'm sorry, I'm always asking
you to translate and your head is somewhere else. Anyway, it's not
exactly clear to me whether they mean whether the, whether the receiving
thing is soft or איידי דרכיכא מבלע. aydi d'rechicha mivla. It,
A is able to absorb into B because A is soft is
I think what the grammar is. But if you think about it,
it's also that B is very easy if B is soft it
makes it easier for it to absorb things that are put into
it, right? Okay? If you put something into even, even a baked
bread, you know, and certainly just flour and oil, it'll absorb if
the B is the, if the מנחה mincha it'll absorb much easier
than a חטאת chatas will absorb. Okay, anyway there maybe it's true
because
let me look yeah, it's the line that says regarding the מנחה
mincha that foods and this is their own addition that foods which
absorb it become holy.
Because it is soft, where do they get to the soft part?
I don't know.
Okay whatever, it's alright. Anyway ואי אשמעינן חטאת, v'ee ashmi'inan chatas, now
if you said
חטאת, chatas, משום דקריא... mishum d'kariya...
A nice soft piece of meat?
Okay, but first of all, in a case where it's not as
absorbent or where the thing coming from it, right, is not, if
you just touch the meat, the meat might have to be hot,
just touching meat normally doesn't transfer. So the thing coming from it
and the thing absorbing into it, the transfer is not as easy.
So since the transfer is not as easy and maybe therefore even
if stuff transfers it doesn't transfer as deeply or as much, maybe
these הלכות halachos would not apply. So maybe it would only apply
to nice soft things like
a מנחה. mincha. אבל חטאת אימא לא, aval chatas eima lo, יש
מנחה וחטאת, yesh mincha v'chatas, if it just told me by חטאת
chatas משום דקריא, mishum dekarya, that's because חטאת chatas like penetrates deeply
in. Again, I guess that's what we're saying
then.
Yeah, I know, I don't exactly understand it. I thought קריא karya
could, I think רשי Rashi says here קריא karya means penetrates in,
but I think חטאת chatas קריא karya also can mean like that
it adheres better, but if somehow, I don't know,
the stuff is, yeah, I don't know. אבל מנחה אימא לא aval
mincha eima lo צריכא. tzricha. So there you have to tell me
both. Okay, you found it, where are we?
Okay, so apparently the assumption is that the מנחה mincha is being
touched by a similar substance type of substance such as a permitted
wafer which would likely be placed in its proximity to it. Accordingly,
since it is soft, it absorbs, means that since the permitted wafer
is soft, it deeply absorbs oil from the מנחה mincha and is
therefore...
Right, so it's reading it that it is talking about the recipient,
the thing that is receiving it is soft and therefore absorbs. Okay.
Yes, because it says the explanation of the מנחה mincha because it
is soft, there is a stronger fusion of the forbidden and permitted
substance so that perhaps the combination principle applies only to such strong
fusion. All right, fine.
Anyway, but it seems like they are translating this as the B,
because מנחה mincha is soft, it allows it to absorb better. What?
But how is it, okay, so if a חטאת chatas is next
to another piece of חטאת, chatas, somehow that's different, which I'm still...
Sure, you don't understand that? I totally understand that. If you've got
a מנחה mincha and if you drop, let's say you have some
חזיר chazir juices around, right, and you drop them on, one hand
you drop them on a wafer, another hand you drop them on
a cooked piece of chicken. Okay, I would definitely think that it's
a bigger problem going into the wafer than it goes into the
cooked piece of chicken. Yeah, I mean if it's raw, I hear
your point, maybe, but even if it's raw you're right, then presumably
it would be pretty absorbent. Right, I guess I'm assuming that it's
cooked. Okay. Anyway. All right, so it needed both to tell me
that even though in some cases the absorption is easier or deeper
or whatever, it really doesn't matter. As long as there's absorption, it's
an issue. Okay. צריכא. tzricha.
Now, חטאת, chatas, מה חטאת אינה באה אלא מן החולין וביום ובידו
הימנית. ma chatas eina ba'a ela min hachullin uvyom uvyado hayemanit. Now
this gets back now to the ברייתא braisa that was taught of
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, because what the גמרא Gemara now said is
we're going to use both מנחה mincha and חטאת chatas to tell
me this הלכה halacha of absorption and it sort of tells me
that even though the absorption might be better or deeper in one
case than the other, it doesn't matter. But the ברייתא braisa itself
doesn't learn absorption from חטאת. chatas. The ברייתא braisa itself learns the
absorption rule from מנחה mincha and learns something else from חטאת. chatas.
So let's see what this ברייתא braisa learns from חטאת. chatas. חטאת,
chatas, מה חטאת אינה באה אלא מן החולין וביום ובידו
הימנית. ma chatas eina ba'a ela min hachullin uvyom uvyado hayemanit. So
same way a חטאת chatas you can only bring from stuff that
is not already
sanctified. Obviously doesn't mean just not sanctified for another קרבן korban because
of course how can something be two קרבנות? korbanos? But as we'll
see, it basically means like an example would be like use your
מעשר שני maaser sheni money to bring a חטאת. chatas. You're not
allowed to do that. Okay, it has to be stuff that's totally
neutral types of stuff. Okay.
וביום, uvyom, and you can only bring it in the day, because
it says by, on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it speaks about bringing
it, it says ביום. bayom. Of course the גמרא Gemara is going
to say that we learn out that from another פסוק pasuk in
general by קרבנות. korbanos. ובידו הימנית, uvyado hayemanit, you have to use
your right hand when you're doing the עבודה avoda because it speaks
about the כהן kohen and אצבעו, etzbao, the כהן kohen and his
finger. And the גמרא Gemara said earlier based on a פסוק, pasuk,
I think by מצורע metzora if I remember correctly, that every time
it uses both the word כהן kohen and finger, we know it
means right hand. So we know these three things by חטאת. chatas.
אף כל אינו בא אלא מן החולין וביום ובידו הימנית. af kol
eino ba ela min hachullin uvyom uvyado hayemanit.
So this is what we learn from חטאת. chatas. We learn the
absorption rule from מנחה mincha according to this ברייתא braisa and from
חטאת chatas we learn these three הלכות halachos to all
קרבנות. korbanos. Now. I'm sorry, wait. But קדשים?
kodashim? But if some people say ולד קרבן vlad korban is like
קודש, kodesh, that means something can come from קדשים. kodashim.
No, no, that doesn't mean... it means like you can't fulfill your
obligation. It doesn't mean that something can't derive קדושה kedusha by being
born from it. It means that you can't bring a קרבן korban
and fulfill your obligation from something that already has some sanctified status.
Okay. וחטאת מנלן, vechatas minalan, where do you know this הלכה halacha
from a חטאת? chatas? אמר רב חסדא אמר קרא, amar Rav Chisda
amar kra, והקריב אהרן את פר החטאת אשר לו, vehikriv Aharon es
par hachatas asher lo, by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
מאשר לו, me'asher lo, it's his. משלו ולא משל ציבור. mishelo velo
mishel tzibbur. A,
don't use your communal funds to buy your קרבנות korbanos for you.
Because כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, I mean actually that makes a lot
of sense. You're representing the ציבור, tzibbur, but this קרבן korban is
not the ציבור's tzibbur's קרבן korban that you're bringing. This is your
personal one. Yes, you're obligated, but it's your personal one, so it
has to come from your own funds. ולא משל מעשר, v'lo mishal
ma'aser, and it has to be fully yours, not like מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni money. That would be the most clear example of what
this הלכה halacha is needed to tell you. Don't use מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni money to go ahead and to satisfy your קרבן korban
obligation. This becomes an interesting question like, you know, in terms of
using מעשר ma'aser money, your צדקה מעשר tzedakah ma'aser money to satisfy
some other מצוה mitzvah obligation. Partly that has to do with how
much do we sort of, you know, model מעשר ma'aser after, you
know, after like the grain מעשר ma'aser and specifically after מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni as opposed to מעשר עני ma'aser ani and so on.
What is the function of the whole idea of מעשר? ma'aser? Is
it a צדקה tzedakah type of a thing in terms of your
obligations to the poor, is it more of a מצוה mitzvah type
of thing, you know, in terms of dedicating sort of
כל אשר תתן לי עשר אעשרנו לך, kol asher titein li asseir
a'asrenu lach, recognizing that it comes from God, so giving it back
to some, to some, you know, godly purpose? Anyway, but it is
an interesting issue that this plays in some discussions about use of
מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, about מעשר ma'aser money. Anyway, ביום, bayom, now
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, fine, we get that that's a הלכה
halacha you learn from חטאת chatat that it has to come from
completely non-sanctified funds. But this idea that it's a daytime, מביום צותו
נפקא, mibayom tzavoto nafka, you don't need that from חטאת. chatat. It
says that this is the, you know, that these are the, these
are the laws that God commanded משה Moshe to bring their קרבנות
korbanot on the day God commanded, ביום צותו, bayom tzavoto, and from
that ביום צותו bayom tzavoto we learn that all קרבנות korbanot can
only be brought during the day. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
fine, כדי נסבה. kideina nasba. Alright, when we said that we learn
day from חטאת, chatat, that's just thrown in, you're right. Day we
learn from a more general
פסוק. pasuk. וידו הימנית, viyado hayemanit, now this idea that you have
to go use your right hand by קרבנות, korbanot, what do we
mean we learn it from חטאת? chatat? מדרבה בר בר חנה נפקא,
miderabba bar bar chana nafka, we learn it from רבה בר בר
חנה. Rabba bar bar Chana. דאמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר ריש
לקיש כל מקום שנאמר אצבע וכהונה אינה אלא ימין. d'amar Rabba bar
bar Chana amar Reish Lakish kol makom shene'emar etzba u'chehuna eina ela
yamin. If it says אצבע, etzba, now the keyword letter here is
the word ו. vav. If it says אצבע etzba and כהונה kehuna
it's only right, well it only says אצבע etzba and כהונה kehuna
primarily by חטאת, chatat, and then you would have to learn it
from חטאת. chatat. But here we're understanding the ו vav to mean
or. Anytime it says אצבע etzba or...
right, exactly, anytime it says
אצבע etzba or כהונה, kehuna, it's right hand. So if that's true,
by every קרבן korban it says כהונה, kehuna, so you don't need
to learn it from חטאת. chatat. So fine, if אצבע etzba or
כהונה kehuna is enough to learn right hand, so again כדי נסבה.
kideina nasba. Eh, we just threw in the right hand, you know,
that was just, that was just for fun. Okay, we just threw
it in as extra. The real thing we learned from חטאת chatat
is that it doesn't come from מעשר ma'aser money. The idea of
day and right hand, that we learn from other places. Okay, ואי
בעית אימא, v'ei ba'it eima, or if you want I can say
no, we really do learn right hands from here. סבר לה כרבי
שמעון, savar lah k'Rabbi Shimon, he's like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon דאמר
אצבע לא בעי כהונה. d'amar etzba lo ba'ei kehuna. If the פסוק
pasuk says אצבע, etzba, you don't need right hand, it doesn't have
to say the word כהונה. kehuna. כהונה, kehuna, if the פסוק pasuk
says the כהן Kohen does it, בעי אצבע, ba'ei etzba, that does
not imply right hand. Okay, if you want the word to, the
תורה Torah to imply right hand, it has to use the word
אצבע. etzba. The word כהן Kohen by itself does not do the
job. And therefore there are plenty of קרבנות korbanot that it says
כהן Kohen and it doesn't say אצבע, etzba, because it's only the
חטאת chatat that you use the finger. Okay, so according to this,
you need to learn from חטאת chatat the idea of right hand.
Okay, so from here according to this ברייתא, baraita, from מנחה mincha
we learn the principle of absorption, and from חטאת, chatat, the גמרא
Gemara says we learn it both from חטאת chatat and מנחה, mincha,
but this ברייתא baraita emphasizes from חטאת chatat we learn the הלכה
halacha it doesn't come from מעשר ma'aser money, and you don't, you
do it in the day, although that we learn elsewhere, and right
hand, although that we might learn from elsewhere as well, or no,
maybe we actually have to learn that from חטאת. chatat.
Okay. אשם, asham, now this ברייתא baraita continues. Again, this ברייתא baraita
learns different things than what we taught yesterday from each one of
these. Okay, so from yesterday you might remember as Michael remembers that
we learn from אשם asham this whole principle that since it's a
male קרבן, korban, the fetus of an אשם asham doesn't become sanctified
because guess what, it doesn't have a fetus. Okay, so and therefore
we learn a more general principle about fetus of קרבנות. korbanot. This
learns something else. אשם, asham, מה אשם עצמותיו מותרין, mah asham atzmotav
mutarin, the same way an אשם asham you can go ahead and
take the bones and, you know, make the bones into, you know,
some type of a, use it to make some type of a,
you know, a cup, a dish, or whatever you want to do,
some bone china, okay, אף כל עצמותיו מותרין. af kol atzmotav mutarin.
It applies to all קרבנות. korbanot. Now of course the question is
how do we know it by אשם? asham? So רש״י Rashi says,
well, you just know it implicitly because since there's no נותר notar
that applies to bones, because נותר notar only applies to meat,
so therefore, and once the חטאת chatat is given to the כהן,
Kohen, they eat the meat, the bones, is it נותר? notar? So
of course they can use their bones for everything.
Okay, so but if you did that for פסח, Pesach, so, well,
yes, that's true. Okay, so, but if you know it logically, why
do you need to apply it from אשם asham to other things?
Just know it logically by everything. So the answer is ah, the
one, one קרבן korban you wouldn't know it by would be עולה,
Olah, because עולה Olah nothing is, well, the skin is given to
the כהנים. kohanim. But other than the skin, it's not basically given
to the כהנים kohanim and basically you burn the bones, you might
not have to if you separated them, but whatever. So therefore from
אשם asham we apply to עולה Olah that guess what, even by
עולה Olah if you separate the bones, you remember we had a
whole discussion before about when they're separate or not separate, you are
actually allowed, that's a pretty shocking... הלכה Halacha. *Halacha*. They are actually
allowed to take the bones from an עולה *Olah* and go ahead
and use it after the and the כהן kohen *Kohein* can use
it for its purposes. Now רש״י *Rashi* still asks, okay, but why
do you learn from אשם *Asham*? You could, if it's logical, if
it starts from a logical position, you could learn it from any
of the קרבנות korbanot. *Korbanot* that are eaten. And one answer is
well, אין הכי נמי *Ein hachi nami* maybe, and the other is
by אשם *Asham* there's an extra פסוק Pasuk *Pasuk* that says לא
יהיה *Lo yihyeh*. So maybe it's not totally logical. Maybe the extra
לא יהיה *Lo yihyeh* should be his the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* tells
us this הלכה halacha *Halacha* by an אשם *Asham* and then allows
us to apply it more broadly.
So as long as we're saying this, remember this is by animal,
it's in mammal sacrifices, would it also be the same for a
bird potentially, right?
Yeah, except the, yeah, I don't see why not. Yeah. Okay. אמר
רבא Amar Rava, פשיטא לי pshita li, *Amar Rava peshita li*, רבא
Rava? *Rava* says, it's obvious to me, דם חטאת Dam Chatas למטה
ודם עולה למעלה *Dam Chatat lemata vedam Olah lemala*. You have a
garment. Now remember, this הלכה halacha. *Halacha* of absorption applies to all
קרבנות korbanot. *Korbanot*. There's a question about, you know, about transferring the
status and cooking in terms of the pot applies to all קרבנות
korbanot, *Korbanot* although there's a question about קדשים קלים *Kodshim Kalim*. But
the one thing that applies only to the חטאת chatas, *Chatat* is
the blood, right? It's if the blood gets absorbed and then you
have to launder it. So רבא Rava *Rava* says here's my scenario.
First a splatter, you know, you can imagine this happening, כהנים kohanim,
*Kohanim* there's blood flying all over the place. You know, first a
splash of עולה *Olah* blood hits the garment. Then a splash of
חטאת chatas, *Chatat* blood hits on top. So if the חטאת chatas
*Chatat* blood hits on top at the exact same spot, the assumption
is it hits in the way that it's not getting absorbed into
the material. It's resting on top of the garment, but it's not
absorbed into the material. So that's the question.
I find that a little bit tough.
All right, whatever, just go with it. דם חטאת למטה ודם עולה
למעלה *Dam Chatat lemata vedam Olah lemala* טעון כביסה *Taun kivisa*. So
דם
חטאת *Dam Chatat*, it's obvious to me if the חטאת *Chatat* came
first and then the עולה *Olah*, טעון כביסה *Taun kivisa*, you have
to launder it. The חטאת *Chatat* came first. What do I care
about the עולה *Olah* blood afterwards? בעי רבא ba'ei Rava, *Ba'ei Rava*,
but here's my question. דם עולה למטה *Dam Olah lemata*, first the
עולה *Olah* hits the garment, ודם חטאת למעלה *Vedam Chatat lemala*, and
then the חטאת *Chatat*. מהו *Mahu*? What's the הלכה *Halacha*? משום נוגע
הוא *Mishum nogea hu*? Is it because the blood is touching the
garment, והא נוגע *Veha nogea*, it's touching even though it's not absorbed?
או דילמא o dilma, משום בלוע הוא *O dilma mishum baluah hu*?
Is it because it got absorbed into the garment, והא לא בלע
*Veha lo bala*, it didn't get absorbed? הדר פשטה *Hadar pashta*, then
he concluded, then he came to a resolution, דאין טעון כביסה *De-ein
taun kivisa*, it doesn't. I love it, you know, when it says
he concluded, no text, no logic, he just, yeah, makes sense it
doesn't. Of course, I, you understand why he's saying that. If the,
if the ritual, if the ritual was to wave it over your
head three times, okay, then you wouldn't say okay, who knows, is
it because it's absorbed or because it touched. But if the ritual
is to launder it, then presumably it's because it got absorbed. And
without absorption, doesn't make sense to have a ritual to launder. Okay,
you wipe it off the surface maybe, but the ritual of laundering,
the same way before we had the idea by the, by the
pot, right? We had this whole question about was it because of
absorption or was it because of cooking, how much if you wanted
to kosher it another way, right? If the ritual is about, you
know, in the case of the pot getting the taste out, and
that's why by a חרס *Cheres* you break it and you don't
do the scalding, so presumably that means that it's rooted in an
idea of absorbing in the walls of the pot. Here too, if
the ritual is about laundering, presumably it's because of an idea of
absorbing into the garment.
Okay, just touching would not get absorbed.
We're touching and we're, right, we're dealing in a scenario where we're
going to assume that it touched, because it's touching and it's riding
on top of a spot that's already crusted with blood from pre,
from another, from the עולה *Olah*, then this is going to just
ride on top without getting absorbed. Okay, you have to just assume
that that's the scenario. אמר רבא Rava *Amar Rava*, now רבא *Rava*
has another question and this is not really about yes.
It's an aside, but did they ever discuss the person who had
the built, the blood spilled is responsible for doing the laundering or
do they send it to the laundry?
That's a question.
Well, they didn't just send it because it had to take place
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*, במקום קדוש *Bimakom kadosh*,
right. I, no, I mean the assumption is it's all communal expenses
here, it's not like we start charging you for you know but
yeah,
exactly, because it's all done in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beit
HaMikdash*, it's not just, yeah. I mean, I think it would be
another interesting question that let's say סתם *Stam* a כהן kohen, *Kohein*
was being irresponsible and he got dirt, or there he was, he
was chomping away at his meat, you know, and he got the
grease on his בגדי כהונה *Bigdei Kehunah*, like which you know, which
is not this ritual, it's just we gotta clean it, like maybe
is that at his expense? That's an interesting question.
Let me just
understand, you know,
we said it only applies to חטאת *Chatat*, but we also have
like that פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* תורת העולה המנחה והחטאת *Torat Ha'olah HaMincha
VeHaChatat*.
For some reason we chose not to learn that that הלכה *Halacha*.
So is it sort of that like you know, we will apply
generally unless there's like a specific פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* תורת החטאת *Torat
HaChatat* maybe, that's why you only apply?
No, you know, it's, no, I don't know, because we do learn
from חטאת *Chatat*, so why do we learn absorption from חטאת *Chatat*
and not the blood thing? My guess would be because the blood
of a חטאת *Chatat* we know is powerful elsewhere. And this principle,
also absorption also exists by a מנחה *Mincha* and it's really just
a question about if something is mixed in, it takes on the
status and so on. A particular ritual around the blood of a
חטאת *Chatat*, we know the power of blood of a חטאת *Chatat*,
you bring it inside. you know,
it affects it, you know, whatever. So, but that's, but yeah, somehow
חז״ל just being guided by סברא, Svara, which things to generalize and
which not. Okay, we don't have a פסוק pasuk that's being quoted.
אמר רבא, פשיטא לי, it's obvious to me, דם על בגדו חוצץ,
dam al bigdo chotzetz, ואם טבח הוא אין חוצץ. ve-im tabach hu
ein chotzetz. Okay, now that we're talking about blood on your garments,
let's talk about another case of blood on your garments. If you
have blood on your garments and you want to go ahead and
put your garment in the מקוה Mikveh because it became טמא, tamei,
not because of the blood, for whatever, it touched a נבלה neveila
or whatever, okay, then the blood is a חציצה chatzitzah because it's
getting in the way of the water touching the garment. But if
you're a butcher and bloodstains on your garment is normal and you
don't go to an effort to remove them in general, then it's
considered אינו מקפיד, eino makpid, you don't care, and it's not a
חציצה. chatzitzah. רבב
על בגדו חוצץ. revav al bigdo chotzetz. If you've got like grease
on your garment, that's a חציצה. chatzitzah. ואם
מוכר רבב הוא, ve-im mocher revav hu, if you're somebody who, you
know, sells greasy stuff and it's common that there are grease stains
on your garment, you're like a short order cook or whatever, so
then אינו חוצץ, eino chotzetz, it's not a problem. Okay, good. That's
a lead up to the question. בעי רבא, here's my question. דם
ורבב על בגדו מהו? dam ve-revav al bigdo mahu? Let's say you
got both a grease stain and a blood stain. So the גמרא
Gemara says, I don't understand the question.
אם טבח הוא, im tabach hu, טיפוק ליה משום רבב—fine, tipok lei
mishum revav the blood isn't a problem, but the grease stain is
a problem. ואם מוכר רבב הוא, ve-im mocher revav hu, and if
he's a like a short order cook,
טיפוק ליה משום דם—the tipok lei mishum dam grease isn't a problem,
but the blood at least is. So what exactly is your question,
רבא? לא צריכא, lo tzricha, you need it in the following case.
דעבד הא והא. de-avad ha ve-ha.
Okay, this guy is both a butcher and a short order cook.
Makes sense, you got your butcher sort of thing in the back,
you're chopping up your meat and you're getting blood splaying around, and
then you're also going ahead—I'm translating מוכר רבב mocher revav as short
order cook, somebody who deals with grease. Okay, so you got both
operations going and you got both spots on your garment. Do we
ignore them both? What do you say? אחדא לא קפיד אהתרתי קפיד,
a-chada lo kapid a-tarti kapid, you know, one type of stain is
fine, like okay, but two different types of stains just makes me
look like a slob. You know, having blood on my garments, people
understand I'm a butcher. Having some grease stains, people understand I'm a
short order cook. Having blood and grease stains, people think I'm a
slob and therefore that I'm מקפיד makpid on. או דילמא, or do
we say, two jobs, אתרתי נמי לא קפיד. a-tarti nami lo kapid.
No, people will understand, I got two jobs, right, it's a hard
economy out there. תיקו, teiku, we don't know the answer. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara leaves it as that, makes it seem a fundamentally
psychological thing. I would have suggested that רבא's question is more similar
to his previous question, which is the following: let's say I've got
a blood stain on here, okay, and let's say I'm a butcher.
I don't sell grease. Okay, and I got a blood stain. The
blood stain isn't a problem. And now I've got a grease stain
on top of the blood stain. But the grease is just sitting
there. It's sort of like his previous question. It's not absorbed in
the garment, it's just sitting there. You know, how much is that
a חציצה? chatzitzah? Like I'll give you an example of how we
have this in הלכה. Let's say I've got a cast on my
arm. So I'm not מקפיד, makpid, the cast isn't a חציצה. chatzitzah.
Let's say on top of the cast, I've got some writing on
top of the cast, or I've got some piece of dirt has
encrusted itself on top of the cast. Do I have to worry
about a חציצה chatzitzah on something that isn't my body? The thing
itself isn't a חציצה. chatzitzah. Let's say I've got some dirt encrusted
on the cast. Do I have to clean the cast? Is the
cast now treated like my body and there can't be a חציצה
chatzitzah on the cast? What? I'm going to the מקוה. Mikveh. A
woman's going to the מקוה, Mikveh, she's got a cast. And on
top of her cast, she's got some crud encrusted on it. Okay,
is that okay? Do we say, look, since the crud isn't on
your body, it's just on the cast, the cast isn't a חציצה,
chatzitzah, no problem? Or do we say, no, the logic, once the
cast isn't a חציצה, chatzitzah, we treat it like your body and
now the crud is a problem? That actually is an interesting debate
in the פוסקים, Poskim, that exact case. So I could understand that
that's רבא's question, not the way the גמרא Gemara reframed it, I
got a grease spot here and a blood spot. No, I got
a blood spot which isn't a חציצה chatzitzah because I'm a butcher
and I got a grease spot riding on top of it. Okay,
do I have to worry about the grease spot which isn't on
my garment but it is on my blood, which would make it
parallel to the previous question? Anyway, it's not how the גמרא Gemara
interpreted. Okay, הדרן עלך דם חטאת. Hadran alach Dam Chatas.
Can I just—yes, before we move to anything else, I just wanted
the מריקה ושטיפה, merika u-shtifa, which we said is by כל קרבן
kol korban according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and not by כל
הקרבנות. kol ha-korbanot. Right. And that is done where? Also in the
עזרה? Azarah? It would be the same place where the קיבוס kibbus
is done or is there like a special...?
I don't know, they maybe they have a separate room, a separate
zone, I don't know.
And we have that מחלוקת machlokeit before for רבי Rebbi and חכמים.
Chachamim. So, you know, that מריקה בחמין ושטיפה בצונן merika be-chamin u-shtifa
be-tzonen according to חכמים. Chachamim. And רבי Rebbi said, you know, you
need הגעלה hagalah and then מריקה ושטיפה. merika u-shtifa. But the חכמים,
Chachamim, for the חכמים, Chachamim, it's the same thing as הגעלה hagalah
for רבי? Rebbi?
Yeah. Okay. All right. Now we switch to—it's very interesting if you
think about it like now how these like recent פרקים perakim are
being organized. Okay, you know, the whole initial beginning of the מסכת
Masechet was about like what is the procedure for קרבנות. korbanot You
know, it starts with types of invalidities, שלא לשמו, she-lo lishmo, פיגול,
pigul, etc. Eventually it gets around to כל הזבחים, Kol Hazevachim, you
know, to tell you where everything is brought, etc., etc. And then
after we're done with the basic procedures and the invalidities, we start
talking about other הלכות. halachot. We have מזבח מקדש, mizbeach mekadesh, you
know, when stuff is put up on the מזבח, mizbeach, does it
get to stay there even if it doesn't belong? That was the
ninth פרק, perek, right? The tenth פרק perek was about was, what
do you call it? Was כל התדיר, Kol Hatadir, the ordering, right?
And now we just finished the eleventh פרק perek was דם חטאת
where these special הלכות halachot about blood on a garment and special
הלכות halachot there, cooking a חטאת, absorbing a חטאת, these things which
are mostly said by חטאת but other than the blood thing generalized
and special rituals around them. Okay, now it's טבול יום Tvul Yom
and what this is about, although the header טבול יום Tvul Yom
might not make you think this, this פרק perek is really dedicated
to the dividing of the קרבנות. korbanot. Which כהנים kohanim get to
eat and get portions in the קרבנות, korbanot and there's really two
questions. One is, am I allowed to eat it? And the other
is, I might be allowed to eat it, but do I get
an am I do I get an equal portion like at the
end of the day they would divide it all up equally? So
could be if, you know, my friend the כהן kohen Michael here,
I'm a כהן, kohen we're all כהנים, but because I was טמא,
tamei, whatever we'll see what the case is, it might be that
now I'm טהור, tahor, Michael will am I allowed to eat it,
I'm טהור tahor now, Michael can share it with me, but I
don't get an equal portion. That I don't get any portion. That's
the question. So there's a difference between when can a כהן kohen,
eat it? Okay, basically if you're not טמא tamei you can eat
it. Okay, and when are you entitled to a portion? Okay, and
that's what we're going to be looking at. Let's read the משנה,
mishnah, get a question in a minute, I want to just start
with the משנה. mishnah.
Okay, what's your comment?
No, because I said because you could have thought that, you know,
you forget about whether you're טמא tamei or not, like it should
just be like a reward for, you know, having served in the
בית המקדש.
Right, so Michael is correct. A lot of the פסוקים psukim say,
and we're going to get to this in the גמרא, Gemara, הכהן
המחטא אתה יאכלנה. Hacohen hamchatei osah yochlenah. A lot of the פסוקים
psukim make it sound like if you did the עבודה avodah with
this particular animal, then you know you get to eat from this
animal, whereas חז"ל Chazal in a more democratic move understood it that
like, you know, it's sort of like tips, actually it's a perfect
example. Right, many restaurants, I don't know if all restaurants, I mean
I guess not all, many restaurants is just you pool the tips
and you divide it. It like recognizes some people luck out that
they get the two-hundred dollar table or the five-hundred dollar table and
the generous tippers, and other people like why should it be unfair,
you know, based on those? We just pool the tips and divide
it. Others say like no, maybe you get a big tip because
people you're, you know, you do things to get big tips or
who knows what? Okay, so the פסוקים psukim sound like it's like
each person gets the tips from their table. Right, you know, the
כהן kohen who did the עבודה, avodah, you know, you're the one
that gets that קרבן. korban. You know, and each person gets the
קרבן korban of the one that they happen to do, whereas חז"ל
Chazal say you pool your tips and you divide them, you know,
so that's actually a very good point. Okay, so let's take a
look at the משנה. mishnah. טבול יום ומחוסר כפורים, Tvul yom umchusar
kippurim, so these are people that are טמא tamei during the day
but they will be טהור tahor that night, okay. I touched a
נבילה, neveilah, I went to the מקווה, mikvah, I can't eat קרבנות
korbanot, until nightfall. Okay, or I had to bring a קרבן korban
because I was, I don't know, a מצורע metzora I guess, or
זב, zav, I guess that would be a better example, a more
common somewhat common, okay. So I got so I was a seven-day
period, it ended with a קרבן, korban, but I'm not טהור tahor
until nightfall. Okay, so so during today when they were doing the
עבודה, avodah, I was טמא. tamei. There's a big תוספות Tosafot to
understand is this really true by מחוסר כפורים, mchusar kippurim, does a
מחוסר כפורים mchusar kippurim have to go to the מקווה mikvah the
day he does his final קרבן korban and is he טמא tamei
until nightfall? Certainly sounds like here that even after you bring your
קרבן, korban, you're טמא tamei until nightfall. So there's a huge discussion.
So here we were, I was טמא tamei that day, but I'm
טהור tahor at night at the end of the day and I
want to have some of this wonderful steak, every day that my,
you know, you don't get to serve in the בית המקדש every
day as a כהן, kohen it's basically two weeks out of the
year roughly is how it would average and then on the רגלים,
Regalim, okay, because they divided them up into houses. But this is
my week or this is my day, you know, and I wanted
to get that big steak barbecue that we're having tonight. אינם חולקים
בקדשים לאכול לערב. Ainom cholkim b'kodshim l'echol l'erev. No, you don't get
a portion. Since you were not able to do the עבודה avodah
in the day, if somebody wants to share their steak with you,
געזונטערהייט, gezinterheit, but you're not entitled to a portion. The basic הלכה
is again, as we said, you don't have to do the עבודה,
avodah, but you have to be fit for having done the עבודה
avodah during the day.
אונן, Onen, נוגע ואינו מקריב, nogei'a v'aino makriv, or our גרסא girsa
is נוגע ואינו מקריב. nogei'a v'aino makriv. Okay, an אונן onen can
touch because you're not טמא tamei if you're if somebody is an
אונן, onen, just lost a relative. Okay, but they're not allowed to
bring the קרבנות. And therefore since they're not allowed to bring the
קרבנות in your state in a person's state of אנינות, aninut, אינו
חולק לאכול לערב. aino cholek l'echol l'erev. Cannot eat that night. The
simple ruling is if you were not able to bring the קרבן
korban that day, even if you're able to at night, you do
not get get a portion.
I mean, I would think that they would be very worried that
like, you know, you're an אונן, onen, you're tarred by אנינות, aninut,
you may have touched the dead body, especially if it's a relative
that you're, you know, sitting...
I guess we don't make that assumption, we would assess it.
But the others אינו נוגע. aino nogei'a.
What, maybe, it's interesting. בעלי מומים, Balei mumim, okay now if somebody
has a blemish of the כהן kohen on his body, בין בעלי
מומים... bein balei mumim... בין בעלי מומים עוברים בין בעלי מומים קבועים,
bein ba'alei mumim ovrim bein ba'alei mumim kevu'im, whether it is a
passing blemish, you know, certainly it's right now, something happened and you've
got some bone out, you know, whatever, something's disfigured, but it's going
to heal or whatever the case might be, or whether או
גבנוח או שבר יד או שבר רגל, o givnuach o shever yad
o shever regel, right,
a broken bone, right, exactly, or it's just, you know, the way
God created you, so in those cases חולקין ואוכלין, cholkin v'ochlin, those
are the exceptions to the rule. Even though they can't do the
עבודה, avodah, they get a portion. Now the Torah's explicit that a
בעל מום ba'al mum is allowed to eat from the קרבנות, okay,
the חידוש chiddush of the משנה mishna is that he's allowed he
gets a portion, even though he can't do the עבודה. avodah. So
he's an exception to the rule. And now the משנה mishna says
the rule of which it just said the exception to it. Okay,
אבל
לא מקריבים, aval lo makrivim, oh, first we clarify, but they can't
bring do the עבודה. avodah. And now כל שאינו ראוי לעבודה אינו
חולק בבשר. kol she'eino ra'uy l'avodah eino cholek babasar. If you can't
do the עבודה, avodah, if you're not fit to do the עבודה,
avodah, you don't get a portion, except for the בעל מום ba'al
mum which we just mentioned a second ago is the exception. Okay,
but the rule is, other than the בעל מום, ba'al mum, if
you can't do the if you're not fit for the עבודה, avodah,
you're not entitled to a portion. וכל שאין לו בבשר אין לו
בעורות, v'kol she'ein lo babasar ein lo ba'orot, and by the way,
don't say fine, but at least give me a portion of the
leather, I want to go ahead and make myself a nice leather
jacket. No, it's all one. If you're entitled to a portion of
the meat, you're entitled to a portion of the leather, if not,
no.
אפילו טמא בשעת זריקת דמים וטהור בשעת הקטר חלבים, afilu tamei b'sha'at
zrikat damim v'tahor b'sha'at haktar chalavim, which is exactly, I mean it's
so funny, it's like all of this is just clarifying the rules
that were true that were clear from the cases above. Somebody that
was טמא tamei when the blood was thrown and you're טהור tahor
at night, at night is when you burn the entrails, okay. Maybe
the point is of the additional חידוש chiddush here is if even
if in practice the entrails of this קרבן korban weren't burned until
night and you were טהור tahor then at night, it doesn't matter,
once again it all goes by the blood. Okay, אינו חולק בבשר,
eino cholek babasar, שנאמר המקריב את דם השלמים. shene'emar hamakriv et dam
hashelamim. The person who brings the blood of the שלמים, shelamim, and
very interesting, the משנה mishna cut out did not have the next
words ואת החלב מבני אהרן, v'et hachelev mibnei Aharon, which undercuts it
completely. We are sort of bracketing, literally bracketing, I love it. Usually
we use bracketing as a metaphor, here literally it's got brackets. Okay,
we're bracketing the word חלב. chelev. It's המקריב את דם השלמים, hamakriv
et dam hashelamim, the blood, לו תהיה שוק הימין למנה. lo tihiyeh
shok hayamin l'manah. You get that portion of the שלמים shelamim if
you do the blood. Now again, be מקריב, makriv, we don't mean
that you literally brought the blood, we're interpreting it as you were
fit to bring the blood. But it's very fascinating that the whole
point is even though you could have participated in doing the אימורים,
imurim, but we're bracketing the second part of that which said says
את החלב. et hachelev. Okay, and we're emphasizing the blood part. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. We'll just start a little
bit into the גמרא. Gemara. מנא הני מילי, mana hani milei, where
do you know this from? This idea that you have to be
fit in order to be entitled to a portion. Top of צד
ט עמוד א. Tzad Tet Amud Aleph. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish
Lakish, אמר קרא, amar krah, the פסוק pasuk says הכהן המחטא אותה
יאכלנה. hakohen hamchatei otah yochlenah. The כהן kohen who does the חיטוי
chituy with it, who you know who does the atonement with it,
with the blood or whatever, brings the קרבן, korban, he gets to
eat from it. הכהן המחטא יאכל, hakohen hamchatei yochal, שאינו מחטא אינו
אוכל. she'eino mechatei eino ochel. Only if you did the עבודה avodah
do you eat, if you don't do it you don't eat. וכללה
היא? v'chlala hi? Is that really the rule? והרי
משמר כולה. v'harei mishmar kulah. What do you mean? Meaning this is
exactly the shift from you get the tips of your table to
where we're all going to split it. Okay, it's not just the
כהן kohen that did that קרבן korban gets to eat it from
it. The whole משמר mishmar gets to do it. Everybody who worked
that day. והרי משמר כולה דאינם מחטין ואוכלין, v'harei mishmar kullah de'einam
mechatim v'ochlin, that they do it. Now again, we're just saying that
because we know that's the הלכה. We don't have a פסוק pasuk,
that proves that. Okay. So it's not literally limited to the person
who does the עבודה avodah itself, that קרבן korban itself. So the
גמרא Gemara says fine, ראוי לחיטוי קאמרינן. ra'uy l'chituy ka'amrinan. So that's
our first exegetical חידוש chiddush and shift. We don't
המחטא hamchatei doesn't mean that you actually did the עבודה, avodah, it
means if you were fit for doing the עבודה, avodah, then you
get a portion of the קרבן. korban. Okay, so that's principle number
one. Okay, one minute, says the גמרא, Gemara, הרי קטן דאינו ראוי
לחיטוי ואוכל. harei katan de'eino ra'uy l'chituy v'ochal. A minor, we're going
to learn later, that minors can't do the עבודה, avodah, which says
איש כתיב, ish ktiv, that you have to be an adult כהן
to be fit for doing the עבודה. avodah. But we're also going
to learn that a minor's allowed to eat from the meat. So
now we get to exegetical shift number two. It's not literally the
one who did it, that was number one. It's anyone fit for
doing it. And it's not יאכלנה, yochlenah, the verse isn't talking about
who eats from it, who's allowed to eat, but who is entitled
to a portion of it. Okay. אלא מאי יאכלנה יחלקנה. ela mai
yochlenah yechalkenah. Gets a portion of it. Okay, got it?
And where's the יאכלנה? yochlenah?
It says הכהן המחטא אותה יאכלנה, hakohen hamchatei otah yochlenah, second line
from the top. We're top of צד ט עמוד א, Tzad Tet
Amud Aleph, right? Okay, so two חידושים. chiddushim. The פסוק pasuk sound
like you have to have done it and only if you did
it do you eat it, although again probably פשט p'shat of the
פסוק pasuk is this יאכלנה יחלקנה yochlenah yechalkenah is probably פשט. p'shat.
Right, because other פסוקים pesukim say כל זכר בכהנים יאכל אותה, kol
zachar b'kohanim yochal otah, all male כהנים are allowed to eat it.
So יאכלנה yochlenah in the פסוקים pesukim probably פשט p'shat is you
know is entitled to eat from it, meaning there's a difference between
permitted and
entitled to a portion. Two points. Number one is you don't have
to literally do it, you just have to be fit for doing
it. And point number two is we're not talking about who's permitted
to eat, we're talking about who's entitled to eat, who gets a
portion. All right, so that's our general rule: if you're able to
do it, if you're fit for doing it, you get a portion.
But then we said before, like the טבול יום tvul yom on
יום כפורים, Yom Kippurim, they can't—they're able to eat, but just, right?
They're able, exactly. They're not entitled, exactly. Okay, יחלקנה. yechalkena. ראוי לחיטוי
חולק, raui lachittui cholek, if you're fit for doing the חיטוי, chittui,
which is also the עבודה avodah of the blood, you get a
portion. שאינו ראוי לחיטוי, she-eino raui lachittui, if you're not fit for
doing the blood work, and even if you're going to be fit
that night to do the אימורים, emurim, אינו חולק, eino cholek, you
don't get a portion. So it's that פסוק, pasuk הכהן המחטא יאכלנה,
hakohen hamchate yochlena, that we say מחטא mchate means fit for חיטוי
chittui and יאכלנה yochlena means entitled to eat, that we learn if
you're fit to do it, you're entitled to a portion. Now, how
about the exception that's in the משנה, mishnah, that the משנה mishnah
just glosses over? הרי בעל מום, harei baal mum, what do you
mean? We got an exception to this rule. A כהן with a
blemish, דאינו ראוי לחיטוי וחולק, de-eino raui lachittui ve-cholek, he can't do
the עבודה avodah and he gets a portion. בעל מום רחמנא רביה.
baal mum rachmana rabyei. No, no, no, no. When the פסוק pasuk
tells you that a בעל מום baal mum eats, it's also telling
you basically that a בעל מום's baal mum entitled to a portion,
because now we're reading 'eat' a lot not just mean permitted to
eat, but entitled. כל זכר בכהנים יאכל אותה לרבות בעל מום. kol
zachar bakohanim yochal otah lirabot baal mum. So the פסוק pasuk that—there's
an explicit פסוק pasuk that says that a בעל מום baal mum
eats, מן הקדשים יאכל, min hakodashim yochel, okay? אך אל הפרכת לא
יבא ואל המזבח לא יגש כי מום בו ach el haparohet lo
yavo ve-el hamizbeach lo yigash ki mum bo whatever the end—I'm not
exactly getting it—ומן הקדשים יאכל. umin hakodashim yochel. But he eats from
the קודש. kodesh. So the פסוק pasuk is explicit that he's allowed
to eat, and from this פסוק pasuk כל זכר, kol zachar, all
males, we're coming to say not only is he entitled, he's actually—not
only is he permitted, he's actually entitled. But now we got a
question. Since the פסוק of entitled is from this generic כל זכר,
kol zachar, what made us choose to read that about a בעל
מום baal mum and not read it about a guy that was,
let's say, a טבול יום? tvul yom? Right? It's because if you're
going to learn it from the פסוק by the בעל מום baal
mum that says he eats it, and to say when the תורה
torah says a בעל מום baal mum eats it means he's entitled
to eat, that's one thing. But if you're just going to tell
me from this פסוק of כל זכר, kol zachar, why do you
focus on a בעל מום baal mum to include and not on
the טבול יום? tvul yom? So the
גמרא gemara says, ואימא כל זכר לרבות טבול יום, ve-eima kol zachar
lirabot tvul yom, maybe it should include a טבול יום? tvul yom?
No, מסתברא בעל מום הוה ליה לרבויי, mistavra baal mum havah lei
lirbuyei, it makes more sense to include a בעל מום, baal mum,
שכן אוכל, she-ken ochel, because a בעל מום baal mum actually was
able to eat during the day itself when the קרבן korban was
being brought. And since he was—what? I mean, but he can't be
מקריב, makriv, but he can eat, that's explicit in the פסוקים. psukim.
So the בעל מום baal mum was not completely shut out of
the מקדש mikdash the day the קרבן korban was being brought. He
was shut out of the עבודה, avodah, but he was—since anyway we're
talking here about being entitled to eat, and when the קרבן korban
was being brought he was permitted to eat, within the within the
category of connected to the eating of this קרבן, korban, the בעל
מום baal mum started off more connected, because during the day the
קרבן korban was brought he was able to eat, whereas the טמא
tamei person was not. Okay?
אדרבה adderaba says
the
גמרא, gemara, טבול יום
הוה ליה לרבויי דלאורתא מחזי,
tvul
yom
havah lei lirbuyei de-le-orsa michezi, okay,
but a טבול יום, tvul yom, you know, at least from the
perspective of being able to be מקריב, makriv, he's more in the
category, because come night he will be able to be מקריב. makriv.
גמרא gemara says, okay, but השתא מיהא לא חזי. hashta miah lo
chazi. That's tonight, that's not now. Now at the critical moment when
the blood is being thrown, who's more connected to this קרבן? korban?
The בעל מום baal mum or the טבול יום? tvul yom? And
the answer is the בעל מום. baal mum. The בעל מום baal
mum right now is permitted to eat this קרבן, korban, he is
somewhere more in the פרשה, parsha, as we would say, and therefore
when it comes to entitled to eat at night, the בעל מום
baal mum is going to be entitled to eat. Okay, so it's
interesting. I would have sort of said the fact that the פסוקים
psukim explicitly underscore that the בעל מום baal mum eats would have
pushed us just to say that therefore he's not only permitted but
entitled, but the גמרא gemara sort of says it from a logical
perspective because even when the קרבן's korban being brought, he's more fundamentally
in the פרשה. parsha. Okay, so we will pick up with this
tomorrow.